okay folks it's time to do it let's
finally answer that question of do
muscle fiber types
change
well I want to start by highlighting
some really interesting initial work in
this area so a famous study done in 1960
really clever what they did is they took
motor units now to explain what that is
briefly a motor unit is an alpha motor
neuron and all the muscle fibers that it
inates so in other words the nerve and
how all the fibers that it activates and
turns on so what he did is and it's
important to sort of know at the
background here all of the muscles all
the fibers in a motor unit are of the
same fiber type so another way to think
about that is the fiber type is
determined by which type of neuron
activates it okay so if it is a type one
or a slow twitch neuron if you will all
the fibers in that motor unit are going
to be slow twitch fibers and if it's
fast twitched going to be fast twitch
fibers so what they did in this famous
study is they came in and said okay
we'll take a slow uh neuron slow motor
unit that has inter that normally inates
and activates slow twitch fibers and
we'll take some that are fast twitch and
we'll cross them so what we'll do here
is we'll cut the fast twitch neuron and
attach it to the slow twitch fibers and
we'll cut the slow twitch neuron and
attach it to the fast twitch fibers and
then we'll watch to see what happens
well it turns out these slow twitch
fibers that were attached now to the
fast twitch
neuron converted and turned themselves
into the other into the neuron fiber
type and the same thing happened to the
other one and so they converted so we've
actually known since 1960 that there are
physiological normative mechanisms that
allow for muscle fiber types to change
so in fact that's not ever really been
the question at least not for the last
60 years or so we know that they can
change the real question has been okay
that's never going to happen in a human
we're not going to cut a nerve and
attach it to another one so we know
mechanisms exist that or in fact we know
them now that are these Mo certain
molecules called inats that are excreted
from the neurons that actually cause the
fiber typic change we've known it
actually happens in in without cutting a
nerve too so there's a phenomenon called
fiber type grouping
so normally as I mentioned not only are
all the fibers in a motor unit of the
same fiber type but they're not
necessarily laying directly next to each
other so if I have a say motor unit that
has five muscle fibers in it those five
fibers are not going to be laying
directly next to each other they're
probably going to be spread out
throughout the muscle this allows
control of f motor
movements well in pathological
situations such as aging or certain
diseases we get what we call fiber type
grouping so what happens here is the
neuron from for whatever reason dies off
but the fibers are still viable and so
the neighboring neurons are are
essentially communicated with or made
aware that the neuron is dead and so
they grow new dendrites and reach out
and attach and
inate those previously uninnervated or
the now uninnervated muscle fibers and
if it happens to grab say a say imagine
it is a slow motor unit and it reaches
out and grabs some no some new fast
twitch motor fibers and brings it into
its motor unit those fibers are then
going to change into be slow so what
happens here are images like this where
normally you have this uh mix and
matching of fast twitch slow twitch kind
of everywhere spread out evenly
throughout the muscle and what happens
in the case of grouping is because so
many neurons die out you get these big
chunks of like fibers so you know huge
chunks of 20 or 30 or 50 fibers that are
all the same fiber type in big bundles
this is one of the things that leads to
lock lack fine tune motor control or
motor
movement so not only do we know is it
physiologically possible to change these
fibers we also know that it happens
under certain normal if you will certain
situations it's not healthy but it is
normal so really to clarify the question
and I I actually will try not to get on
too much of a tangent right here but
this is a great example of a lot of the
miscommunication and Science and
otherwise simply comes down to asking
bad questions so the question of do
fiber types change is a terrible
question it's not even remotely
debatable of course they change the more
specific and question that people are
generally trying to ask when they ask
that is okay well do they change with
different types of exercise training
this actual question about the
plasticity of fiber types with different
types of exercise training has been
actually around for a very long time in
fact in ear early 19 early late 1960s
early 1970s a very famous physiologist
muscle physiologist
named Dr ederton came up with a
beautiful study and he wanted to answer
this question so he looked at the animal
models and he used histo chemistry and
he said okay what if I put these animals
through some swim training and so I
don't know if this is actually a picture
of the actual study although obviously
it's not but this is effectivly what
happens in fact you could look elsewhere
to figure out what it actually takes to
swim train a mouse and it's not that
great but nonetheless so he did this
first initial study in 1969 and said
whether or not fiber types change which
exercise train
training and then he found essentially
nothing so no change at
all a couple of years later another
extremely famous uh muscle physiologist
um Dr gulnick came out with a study that
said okay let's just simply compare
athletically train people to
non-athletic train to see if they have
different fiber type profiles so what
he's he what he did is is took sedentary
individuals and compared their muscle at
rest to uh endurance runt trained
individuals and what he found found was
a significant difference in fact what he
found is those that were highly
endurance trrain had way more these slow
twitch
fibers keep one thing in mind though
take a look at that image what do you
automatically know about that image this
is hiso chemistry right black white so
although what this is very very
important we have to keep in mind the
limitations all this simply told us was
one there was more slow twitch now than
fast twitch it didn't give us any of
that specificity and two we can't
necessarily say whether this was nature
or ner
because we don't know what either one of
these people looked like so in other
words the athletes could have simply
been born with a more slow switch so
they chose to engage in endurance
activities because they're pre
gentically exposed to being better at
them but it was still an awesome paper
an amazing study and Prov provided a lot
of great
information so being the phenomenal
scientist Dr gck was he said let me
follow that up and actually do a
training study so in this time instead
of comparing sedentary people to
endurance trained people let's take
sedentary people and endurance train
them and see what happens over time well
unfortunately he found no change at all
in either the type ones or the type twos
again notice the terminology type type
one two hist chemistry
right in fact just to summarize a about
a decade of research for you up to 1976
here's what we knew about this question
number one there were definitely
correlations between fiber type profile
and perform performance we knew that
those that had more slow fibers had
better endurance and the inverse had
actually been shown several times as
well those that were had more fast
fibers or faster stronger better at more
anerobic Sports so that part was clear
in humans at this point we also know
that inactivity things like uh nerve
cutting or or massive inactivity the
stuff that I showed you at the very
beginning simulations um all that stuff
did cause the fibers to change
but fiber types did not change with
exercise training in humans so this had
been done several times with different
endurance training stuff there was also
a fantastic paper by Thorson and their
group in 1975 that showed Sprint
training didn't either so we know fiber
type correlates to Performance it
changes in very weird simulations and
cross cutting of nerves and and
pathologies but it's not changing with
exercise training in fact I think most
of the people that make comments about
this and write chapters and things
online I think they must have stopped
doing their research at this point
because up to this time it was pretty
clear answer and it made a lot of sense
unfortunately A lot's changed since
1976 in fact just a few L years later a
couple of different groups did a series
of really really interesting studies uh
these were done in both endurance
running and endurance
cycling and they just to summarize sort
of
everything they want wanted to know do
the type ones 2 A's and 2 B's change now
remember I'm using type 2B not 2x
because at the time they were referring
them to type 2p we now know them to be
2x but either way we're also using type
so we know they used hemistry here so
what they found was no change in the
type one fibers but an increase in 2 a
and a decrease in
2B
aha enter the controversy enter you
pulling your hair out by by your own
threads because people are now having
all this evidence for years to suggest
they don't change and all of a sudden
the next year two different paper show
it
changed what happened remember the major
limitation of hemistry for fiber typing
purposes was it lacked
specificity this is going to be a major
po portion of what we're talking about
here we have to split things up into one
or 2 B at most to get 2 a and 2 B we
have to call them black white and in
some level of gray
there hold that thought an amazing study
in 1978 came out and if you've ever done
a study before or think you've had a
hard workout picture what it must have
been like to be in this study so this
was a training study I believe it was
eight weeks long what they or sorry much
longer than that but what they
effectively did is let's try four
different training Styles back to back
to back and let's take biopsies in
between all of them and see what happens
over
time and what they noticed was after
weeks of jogging training and then a
biopsy and then Sprint training and a
biopsy and then jogging biopsy Sprint
training was a transition from type 2
one to your intermediates when you went
from jogging to Sprint training and then
from your type two
intermediates back to type ones when you
did more endurance training so this is
initially an an indication that maybe
sprinting type training causes us to
transition from type one to type 2C
which remember earlier we think the
hybrids are simply fibers caught
transitioning from in this case a one to
a 2 a but then when we started doing the
steadystate endurance training again and
for the record this is the jogging stuff
was probably I can't remember exactly
but it was most likely something like 30
to 60 Minutes of of of five to six days
a week or somewhere like that at a
consistent pace so not intervals
sprinting was more of the interval type
of stuff but nonetheless when we do the
jogging stuff like right here we go from
the two C's more towards the type ones
indicating that type of training causes
a conversion back to slow twitch well
they further elucidated and extrapolated
a little bit and suggested what's
actually happening is exactly what I
alluded to so during the Sprint training
we're trying to transition from a one
all the way to a 2B 2x right then when
we start the jogging training again we
actually make our way back from being a
2B or a 2X all the way down to our
original type ones
this was the first study that really uh
in a complex fashion
outlined what's possible in that not
only is there a conversion with exercise
training but it's happening back and
forth so our conclusions are in 1978 are
a little bit different than those in
1976 so number one fibers actually
quickly change with exercise training
but only if typed with high specificity
so in this particular study and the one
before but in this one even more so when
we allow ourselves to identify these
hybrid or in between fibers now we start
to see change but when we use the paper
like the gck study that only allowed us
to do say one and two we don't notice a
change so more specific more accurate
fiber typing methods are now leading to
us are giving us the ability to pick up
on the changes in fiber type with
exercise number two when we do endurance
type of training we it looks like we're
seeing a fast to slow twitch trans
transition and when we do anerobic
training we see the opposite of slow to
fast
transition we're going to jump all the
way up to 1994 so a classic paper by
Anderson and their colleagues came out
in this day and in fact what's
interesting about this and the reason
we're skipping all the way up to now is
the answer hasn't really been different
since this original 1994 paper the
reason I'm making this video in 2016
though is for some reason people still
haven't gotten this memo so hasn't
really changed since 94 to now in fact
almost every study that's used the
proper
methodology has seen the exact same
result for the most part if you adopt a
sedentary lifestyle this would be maybe
some minimal physical activity but no or
very limited structure to exercise
whether this is a party lifestyle
nutrition sleeping or not that doesn't
really matter and it also doesn't appear
to matter what gender age what muscle
group we test as you increase or I
should say as you decrease your physical
activity the amount of hybrid fibers you
have increases so your pure type ones or
your pure 2a's start being converted
into the type one 2as and the type 2 a
2x's or even in theory the 12
a2x all right so if you want a little
more science my my colleague Dr Jimmy
Bagley published a phenomenal uh
literature review on this topic and I
think his graph highlights it quite
clearly so what he did is each one of
these different colored bars is a
different study so you see he's
representing eight studies here but he
certainly looked at all of them and over
the last say almost 25 to 30 years of
research in this area whenever we use
the single fiber uh electris
method this which is the only one that
allows us to actually accurately
identify these hybrids we always see
this pattern when you're physically
inactive the peers go down the ones and
the two a
but at the same time the total hybrids
go up now we don't exactly know why
we're totally guessing but the
speculation is you've got hybrid or
you've got fibers that are sitting there
basically saying like what do you want
me to do do you want me to be really
fatigue resistant or do you want me to
be really powerful right both end of our
spectrums well if you're not going to
tell me what to do I'm going to sort of
sit here in the middle I don't want to
have any specificity in function because
I don't have any specificity in
Direction tell me you want me to be
oxidative fatigue resistant tell me to
be slow twitch I'll move there tell me
to be fast twitch I'll move there but
until you tell me what to do probably
the most evolutionarily advantageous
thing is to sit somewhere in the
middle right so to summarize that
activity equals spe specific changes and
less hybrids so the inverse is actually
happening it doesn't necessarily matter
whether you pick uh resistance exercise
intervals biking running swimming
strength training or or any combination
in fact very little has been done
outside of those those standard areas of
your classic resistance exercise three
sets of 10 type of stuff your classic
steady state endurance a little bit of
stuff on some intervals but not much all
the other types of training that we know
exist haven't been examined but it seems
to really not matter any sort of
physical activity any sort of rigorous
exercise causes specific changes and a
decrease in hybrids endurance type of
training looks like it will slightly
increase the type amount of type ones
you have and and more speed strength
power-based exercises seems to increase
the type two ways you have so the
changes are specific to the type of
training you're doing but regardless of
that the hybrids go
down all right so again these hybrids
provide some level of specificity in
your training and this is probably why
uh we have them around where it's why
it's a little bit advantageous to have
the ability to kind of
flip-flop I will tell you very very few
Laboratories are are are are focusing on
this area so we have a ton still to
learn but it's really at this point
unquestionable whether or not physical
activity or any kind of training can
cause a fiber type
transformation it's just been shown in
every study that's used the accurate
fiber typing methods for the last two
and a half decades right over 30 studies
now probably getting closer to 40 or
maybe even
50 in fact to highlight this even even
more a figure that Dr Bagley and I are
working on perhaps by the time you see
this video this will be published but
what this really shows is again a a
composite of a bunch of different
studies and it kind of puts athletes on
different spectrums I'm not going to
walk you through this through this
entire slide but you can pause it and
take a look at it yourself but basically
what we're showing here is more or less
hybrids right those that are physically
trained have less hybrid those are
inactive sedentary maybe recreationally
active tend to have more those that have
more fast switch fire ders competitive
sprinters bodybuilders and those over
here Runners distance Runners distance
Runners have more slow
twitch up to this point we have pretty
good information on the fiber type
qualities of your steady state endurance
athletes swimmers cyclists and Runners
we also had a decent amount on
powerlifters weightlifters some
bodybuilders but we never had any
information about people in the middle
if you look at the sport of mixed
martial arts it's really complicated
because of course athletes have to be
very fast but at the championship level
like this individual athlete you got to
be able to prepare to fight for 25
minutes so this is maximal heart rate up
and down this is your worst interval
workout your 10 seconds on 10 seconds
off but you got to do it for 25 minutes
so you have to be fast strong of course
technically and tactically sound but you
have to also have some massive endurance
abilities so what's an athlete look like
from the type level that has these super
high strength and power qualities but at
the same time has the ability to repeat
maximal effort over and over and over
and over again does that mean they just
have a lot of fast switch fibers that
are really have a lot of endurance
quality do they have a lot of slow
twitch fibers but generate Force some
other way or is it totally
different well it turns out in this
particular study you can see the athlete
right here in purple most individuals
have about 20 to 40 50% of their muscle
fibers are slow twitch that would be
pretty normal so you can see in the
yellow bar here a sedentary gray is
untrained white is recreationally active
there seems to be a normal number of
about 30 or 40% of the individual muscle
fibers coming from slow
twitch most people again you'll see the
your yellow and gray bar and white out
here have somewhere between 20 to 30 to
40% of their fibers in any of the hybrid
States so that's what total hybrid means
and with most people being somewhere
between hey 10 to 20% one 12 a 10 to 20%
2 a2x somewhere in there that would
leave most people in the yellow gray and
white bars again being somewhere between
20 and
40% fast
switch this fighter however was almost
70% pure
2A this is incredibly High we almost
never see this high and we would
certainly never see it in an athlete
that has to also simultaneously mean so
much of an endurance performance
background right you'll also notice out
here the two x's and we'll get to that
in a little bit later but this is what
made us really started to question these
things to start to think about you know
what maybe simply studying your swimmers
triathlons and endurance Runners
comparing those two bodybuilders maybe
that's not telling us the whole answer
are providing us all the information we
need to know about the importance of
muscle fiber types right so what about
things like weightlifters we still don't
have any accurate fiber typing data on
competitive weightlifters what about
folks that do things that are more
interval based or mixed methods so some
people that maybe do a kettle bell or
dumbbell workout one day and then do
high-intensity intervals uh Sprint uh
Hill Sprints one day then maybe go to
the pool and swim for an hour the next
day heavy deadlifts the last day
we don't have any idea what those mixed
or or multiple combinations look like we
don't have any idea surprising enough
you would think this is true but we
don't know what the fiber type profile
looks up of a professional baseball
player how about a professional
basketball no idea these as if actually
never been done we've got an complete
Darth of information in that
area we also can't answer very practical
training questions like the one you see
down here what if you go to the gym and
do three sets of 15 is that going to
cause the same fiber type profile as 15
sets of three how about five sets of six
I don't have any idea we certainly know
that those give different outcome
measures right but we don't know if
that's actually causing a difference in
fiber trap transformation or not my
point all this is although we do know
quite a bit and there's almost no way we
can question the overall plasticity of
muscle fiber types with physical
activity we have way more questions
about this than we'll ever know answers
we have we haven't yet to examine gender
almost no information is available on
the muscle fiber types of females
literally a handful a small couple of
Studies have been done on females we
also don't know about muscles I would
say 90% or more of the studies on fiber
type have been done what's called the
vastest lateralis this huge muscle out
here on this amazing athlete right the
lateral quadricep muscle there's been a
little bit done on the gastrock which is
this big muscle right here in your calf
and the Solus which is a smaller one in
your calf a tiny bit of the deltoid
which is your shoulder a little bit on
the triceps the back of your arm and the
biceps but almost minimal in those areas
right what about glutes hamstrings right
all the other traps lats we have
forearms we have almost no information
at all there's some stuff from the 90s
and before looking at cadavers but
nothing in live humans and nothing at
all in this specificity with this
specificity and then to make it even
worse what about about nutrition what
about high carb diets high fat diets
high protein low protein fasting diets
timing diets eating at night but not at
during the day things like this we have
absolutely no information at all in
those areas so I can't in good faith
give you any suggestions about what
those types of things do to your fiber
type
profile so to wrap this stuff all up in
summary do muscle fiber types change
well I hope at this point you're pretty
convinced that yes of course they do and
I don't really think it's even
questionable well no I know it's not
questionable at
all we do see a quite excessive
transition into fast so it does seem
that your fast twitch fibers are much
more appliable uh you'll get bigger
changes and'll happen much faster now
some people will still tell tell you
that you can't transition into slow
which is completely bogus but I will
admit that it is much less prevalent it
seems to either take a much longer time
frame or um much more severe situation
so you're you're not necessarily going
to transition as easily into slow twitch
as you are a fast twitch but it is still
possible with exercise training to have
that and since you all like details and
I this is one of the most common
questions I get you want to know how
much can it change are we talking a 1%
change or 800% change well I don't know
right we don't have any long-term
studies uh we don't really have too many
things that are more than like 12 weeks
to be honest so I'll give you some rough
numbers here and these are highly
variable but I would say something like
if the if the training is less than a
year long you're probably looking at 20
to 30% or less of a change so if you're
40% 2A you after a year of training you
might be 50 55% I I really don't know we
see you more like an 8% change over 12
weeks but that's probably not going to
continue on for forever I just don't
know what I do know though is after a
year those numbers can become enormous
we have situations in fact where some
individuals under extreme situations uh
these would be things like people with a
spinal cord injury where a hamstring or
glutes not activated for 10 years or
more we see 30 40 50 7 80% changes in
fiber type so that's the best I can give
you I know that might be a touch
frustrating but hey that's the that's
where science is at right now you want
to do something about it let me know
we're trying to right but we need some
help
some really exciting new information in
the last couple of years has showed us
that in fact maybe there's more to these
fast and slow TCH fibers than we
originally thought so this is an idea uh
called the nuclear domain this is these
are beautiful images so take a look at
these two fibers over here right one of
them is a fast twitch and one of them is
a slow twitch fiber what we now know are
things like there are differences in the
amount of nuclei it it looks like at
this point slow touch fibers have more
nuclei remember that from the very
beginning the nuclear would hold your
DNA tell your s to grow shrink replicate
it also looks like your slow twitch
fibers have more satellite cells so
satellite cells sit on the outside of
the of the fiber or the cell and when
you need more nuclei they move in get
differentiated and become a nuclei right
so this is if you're not familiar with
satellite cells this is one of the most
hottest Topics in all of physiology
right now one of the hottest ones uh
because it seems to be like that's one
of your major limiters with Plus
once you run out of satellite cells you
can you can't differentiate into M
nuclei you don't have any nuclei you
can't grow shrink
repair right with all that in mind it
seems like the myonuclear Doane size is
larger in your fast switch fibers so a
myuc the monuclear domain basically says
okay how much domain or how much space
does each nuclei control a smaller
myclear domain appears at this point to
be advantageous because that means each
nuclei is controlling a smaller region
this just means you're going to have
faster replies so imagine you open up a
business and you have another office in
Vancouver and another one in South
Africa well if you have a regional
manager set up at every location when a
printer goes out or a phone line breaks
it's very easy to repair those things
but if you only have one Center
controlling you know an entire continent
it's very slow to make changes right so
now we are just uncovering these things
you can see this paper just came out in
2015 there's more and more coming out
but it's a really exciting area that in
fact we're working on too um but that's
about as much as we know at this point
we have almost done nothing in the area
of humans and so we'll see if this holds
true in our space as well or what other
things we can
uncover so at this point in the video
we've had a full discussion what fiber
types are and I think we've made it
pretty clear that whether or not they
change with exercise and of course our
answer is yes and in both directions
actions